in the previous lecture
i described various computational problems regarding phylogenetic trees and networks
today i'm going to show you how to solve them
let's start with a quick reminder of what we learned in the previous lecture
in the last lecture
i provided the definitions of phylogenetic trees and networks
and explained the concept of subdivision trees
that is underlying trees inside a possibly very complicated phylogenetic network
phylogenetic networks that have at least one subdivision tree are called tree based networks
then we looked at seven computational problems concerning subdivision trees
the problems are the decision problem search problem deviation quantification problem
counting problem listing problem optimization problem and the top k ranking problem
in this lecture i'll focus on the first six problems
since the analysis of the last one is a bit too technical
but anyway the point of today's lecture is that
all of these problems can be solved by one theorem
which i call a structural theorem for phylogenetic networks
this theorem is very useful
because it works as a common framework for solving different problems in a unified way
in fact as we'll see later today
it gives rise to a set of fast algorithms for variety of problems on subdivision trees
similarly to many other structure theorems
including the structural theorem for finite dividing groups
which will be reviewed in the next slide
the statement of this theorem can be divided into two parts
firstly it clarifies the simplest building blocks for building all rooted binary phylogenetic networks
more precisely as i'll explain later
It provides a unique canonical decomposition of rooted binary phylogenetic networks
then based on the canonical decomposition
it characterizes the set of all subdivision trees in the form of a direct product
to give you a clear picture
let's quickly review some basic knowledge of abstract algebra before going into more detail
among the many structure theorems established in various branches of mathematics
perhaps the most famous is the structural theorem for finite dividing groups
which is also known as the fundamental theorem for all finite abelian groups
Roughly speaking it states that
every finite abelian group
can be uniquely decomposed as a direct product of finite many cyclic groups
in much the same way as the prime factor decomposition of natural numbers
the application of the theorem includes
the problem of counting finite Abelian groups of order n
for example how many Abelian groups are there of order 144
the number 144 is decomposed as 2 to the power 4 times 3 to the power 2.
there are 5 different partitions of the integer 4
and there are two different partitions of the integer 2.
so the number of all the possible choices
namely the number of abelian groups of order 144 equals five times two
of course if you wish
it's also possible to list all the possible choices
all the Abelian groups of order 144
as you can see here
so the goal of today's lecture is to show a structure theorem
relevant to our context
and to understand how it helps us solve the problems we saw earlier
okay so to begin with let's have a look at this obvious but important remark
suppose we want to construct a subdivision tree of a tree based network n
remember any subdivision tree is a spanning tree of n
so the set of vertices of t must be identical to the set of vertices of n
this means that there is no choice about the vertex set
So the only point to be considered is which arcs to be chosen
obviously if we arbitrarily choose a subset s of a n
then s may or may not induce a subdivision tree of n
if we carefully choose an admissible set of arcs
then we can get a subdivision tree
as indicated by the red lines
but if we choose a wrong one as indicated by the blue lines here
the resulting subgraph is not subdivision tree of n
in fact it may not be a tree
may not have a unique root
or may have a leaf set other than x
then a natural question arises
what are the rules that determine whether or not s induces a subdivision tree of n
this question was initially addressed by francis and steel in their first paper
On tree based networks
they characterized when s introduces subdivision tree
by using three conditions that are very easy to understand
first as illustrated in the two figures at the bottom left
If n contains an arc either arriving at the vertex of in degree 1
or leaving the vertex of out degree 1
we must choose it
it's easy to see that
if we exclude such an arc from s
then s would induce a subgraph having a leaf not in x or an extra root vertex
second as illustrate in the middle
if n has two arcs entering a vertex of in degree two
then we must choose exactly one of them
because we want to construct a tree
it's clear that we can't choose both of them
obviously we can't ignore both of them either
because otherwise we would have a subgraph with an extra root
third as shown on the right
if n has two arcs leaving a vertex of out degree two
we must choose at least one of them
satisfying these three is a necessary and sufficient condition
for s to induce subdivision tree of n
this means that we can automatically get a subdivision tree of n
By simply selecting x to satisfy these three conditions
from this it follows that
there is a one-to-one correspondence between the set of subdivision trees of n
and set of the arcs of n satisfying the three conditions
let's call such a subset of a an admissible
then we can rephrase the problems we saw earlier
so the decision problem asks whether or not there is an admissible arc set
the search problem asks for one admissible set
the counting problem asks how many admissible arc sets there are
The listing problem similarly asks to generate all admissible subsets of an and so on
to solve these problems i now introduce a key concept
that is a maximal zigzag trail in a rooted binary phylogenetic x network
intuitively a zigzag trail in n is a subgraph of n such that
the sequence of arcs forms a repetition of up and down movements
as indicated by the green line here
more formally a sub graph set of n is said to be a zigzag trail in n
If there is an ordering of its arcset such that
any two consecutive arcs have a common head or tail
for example the green sub graph on the left is a zigzag trail in this phytogenic network
Because if we order the four arcs of it from left to right as a1 a2 a3 a4
Then a1 and a2 share the tail
a2 and a3 share their head
and a3 and a4 share the tail
so there exists such a permutation of its arcs
notice the difference from the red sub graph on the right
which is an usual directed path
where each arc is oriented in the same direction
for this red sub graph
there is no such a permutation
so it's not a zigzag trail
in addition we say zigzag trail is maximal
if it is not a part of another strictly longer zigzag trail in the network
for example the green sub graph at the bottom is a zigzag trail in the network right
but it's not maximal because it's a sub graph of the previous zigzag trail
"by contrast, the previous one is maximal"
because we can't extend it to a longer zigzag trail in the network so it's maximum
okay so why is the concept of maximal zigzag trail so important for us
because it turns out every rooted binary phylogenetic network is decomposed into its maximal zigzag trails
that are uniquely determined
as you can verify easily
"the zigzag trails, a rooted binary phylogenetic network"
can be classified into only four types
as illustrated on the right
those that look back to the starting point are called crowns
and those that don't loop and form the letter m are m-fences
those that have an odd number of arcs to form the letter n are n-fences
and those that form the letter w are w-fences
so for example this network on the left is decomposed into
a maximal m-fence with two arcs
another maximal m-fence with two arcs
a maximal m-fence with six arcs
a maximal w-fence with two arcs
a maximal n-fence with three arcs
and a maximal n-fence having only one arc
by the way in a binary network
No two maximal zigzag trails have a common arc
so as i demonstrated just now
we can obtain the set of maximal zigzag trails
by visiting each arc of the network exactly once
so it follows that the maximal zigzag trail decomposition can be computed in linear time
"in the size of n,in the size of the input network"
anyhow the important thing is
such decomposition is always uniquely determined by each network
so no matter how complex it is
any rooted binary phylogenetic network can be canonically decomposed into
a unique set of such simple pieces
then we can immediately obtain this useful lemma
it's very similar to the previous conditions established by francis and steel
but the important difference is that
we don't need to look at the entire arcset of the network
once we have decomposed the network into its unique maximal zigzag trails
all we have to do is to find an admissible arcset within each maximal zigzag trail
And then take the union of those admissible subsets
okay so for example
i now demonstrate how to find an admissible arcset of the maximum Zigzag trail
indicated by the red line in the right figure
suppose we have decided to include this arc as a member of s
in this case according to the condition 3
we may or may not pick the next one
but here we do them
by the condition 2 we can't use the next arc
by the same reason we then have to select this arc
and we can't select the next one
finally by the condition one or condition three
we must include the last one
thus we have obtained an admissible subset within this maximal zigzag trail
in the same manner
we can even explicitly represent the family of all admissible arcsets
for each type of maximal zigzag trail
as you can see easily in the case where i is a crown
there are two admissible arcsets
in the case where Zi is a maximal m-fence
the number of possible choices is half the length of set i
when zi is a maximal n-fence
there is the only one admissible arcset
Finally in the case of maximal w-fence
there's no other admissible arcset
so from these observations it follows that
if n has a maximal w fence
then there's no subdivision tree of n
on the other hand if n is composed of the other types of maximal zigzag trails
then simply by choosing one of the possible choices within each maximal zigzag trail
"then by doing so we can create, we can construct any subdivision tree of n"
therefore the family of admissible arcsets
Namely the set of all subdivision trees of a tree based network
can be expressed as a direct product of the family of all possible choices
within each maximal zigzag trail
this is the second part of the main result
so putting the two results together
We obtain a structural theorem for rooted binary phylogenetic network
from this structural theorem we can derive a number of algorithms
as a preprocessing
each algorithm starts by decomposing an input network n into maximal signal trails
Which requires linear time as i explained earlier
importantly having characterized the set of subdivision trees in terms of a direct product
we can recognize the integers that constitute the number of subdivision trees
Like prime factorization
so we can count number alpha how many subdivision trees there are
simply by multiplying the number of admissible arc sets
within each maximum zigzag trail
notice that this algorithm can solve the decision
and counting problems simultaneously
Because number alpha is non-zero
if and only if the network is tree based
in this example as we have seen
The network contains a maximal w-fence z5
so alpha n is equal to 0.
of course by contrast
if the input network is w-fence free
as you can see on the left
then alpha should be a positive integer
that represents the number of subdivision trees of these tree based networks
this network
the algorithm for the deviation quantification problem needs some explanation
but it's quite easy
it simply counts how many maximal w-fences there are
and returns the number as the deviation measure for the network
this algorithm is correct
because if n contains the forbidden component
namely a maximal w-fence
then we can break it just by attaching one additional leaf to it
therefore computing delta
which is defined to be the minimum number of extra leaves
necessary to convert n into tree base network
is nothing more than counting the number of maximal w-fences in n
the search problem is also easy to solve
given a tree based network and by picking any admissible subset
within each maximal zigzag trail and taking the union of the selected arcs
then the set of those arcs induces a subdivision tree of n
remarkably the optimization problem can be solved easily in linear time
in a quite similar way
this is because the union of the best arc set within each maximal zigzag trail
induces the best subdivision tree of the network
in other words
we can automatically get the global optimum simply by collecting an optimal solution
Within each maximal zigzag trail
So we see that there's no need to list and examine all the possible subdivision trees of n
which is really nice
then how can we list all of them if we wish to do so
the listing problem is similar to the search problem
so just the same as we did earlier
the algorithm outputs our first solution in linear time
this is the same one as before
And then output all subdivision trees of n one after another t1 t2 t3
until it has listed all subdivision trees
the algorithm described here belongs to the most efficient class of listing algorithms
since it runs with a linear time delay
Namely it's an algorithm with the following three properties
first the algorithm can output a fast solution in linear time
linear time in the input size
second the algorithm can continue to generate another solution one after another
such that the time between any two consecutive solutions to outputs
is bounded by a linear function of the input size
third the algorithm can decide in linear time in the input size again whether to terminate
linear time delay listing algorithms are really nice
because their running time is linear in both input size and output size
okay so we have seen various algorithms derived from the structural theorem
i'll finish today's lecture with a demonstration of
data analysis using one of those algorithms
so imagine that there is a biologist studying the evolution of eight different species
and he wants to reconstruct the evolutionary tree from some biological data
he took into account all the possible evolutionary paths
and ended up with a network shown on the left
the network is far from a tree
so he came to ask you whether or not it's meaningful to analyze such a network
Indeed the network is so complex as a honeycomb
but it's still a tree-based network right
once you have obtained the maximum zigzag trail decomposition
as described here
you can quickly see that by a hand calculation the number of subdivision trees of this network is 5040.
it's a fairly large number that tells us how complicated the network is
but notice that it's still much smaller than the number of all phylogenetic trees with eight leaves
so fortunately for the person you can conclude that
Although the network is not tree like at all
it does contain meaningful information for the search for the correct tree
Okay as this example indicates
the algorithm described today are expected to find many practical applications
in various real world settings
okay this is the end of my lecture
I hope my videos provided a good introduction to discrete mathematical biology